DAVID KRENTZLIN

Address Hinrich-Thieß-Str. 52d

22844 Norderstedt

Germany

E-Mail <u>david.krentzlin@gmail.com</u>

Github https://github.com/certainty

Website http://www.lisp-unleashed.de/me



PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

I'm a software engineer with management experience and I strive in environments which require technical expertise as well as good communication and leadership.

In my roughly 18 years as a software engineer I have worked on multiple high traffic, distributed services in all stages of their life-cycles and in multiple domains and helped to scale them operationally and organisationally.

I care about good culture and try to increase my understanding of the environments, teams, systems, values and practices that enable organisations to sustain in an industry, that is fast-paced and requires constant feedback and learning.

SKILLS

self driven learning very good communication with groups and individuals very good coaching, management and leadership good agile software delivery good software design / software architecture good Scala, Rust, Ruby, Haskell good GraphQL, APIs, Distributed Services good Compilers / Programming Languages familiar familiar Scheme, Elixir, Redis, MySQL, PostgreSQL

LANGUAGES

German native English fluent Icelandic novice

WORK EXPERIENCE

Team Lead Architecture New Work SE

Mar 2020 - Today

API Infrastructure Team

lead a team of six software architects & software engineers in a newly created solution architecture area. As a platform team we build and operate the central GraphQL API, which is used by 200+ engineers to build their products faster and more robust. As a former individual contributor in the team I took on the leadership position and helped my engineers to be self-sustained, autonomous and achieve the team's objectives.

- build the newly established team and foster good collaboration, team ownership and consistent delivery
- help to establish data driven software delivery and continuous improvement processes for consulting and platform projects
- drive architectural decisions and give architectural guidance for the engineering organisation
- enable my direct reports and support them in achieving their objectives and growing them in their functions
- facilitate decision making, group learning and continuous improvement to help the team take ownership of their platform

leveraged knowledge

leadership, management, communication, agile methods, coaching, project management

Senior Software Engineer New Work SE

Dec 2015 - Mar 2020

XING One - GraphQL Gateway (2017 - 2020)

I was part of the core platform team that planned, designed, developed and rolled the central GraphQL Gateway which is called XING One. I accompanied the service through the early project phase, when it was scaled to the whole organisation and when it reached maturity. The platform is now used by 200+ product engineers, to build their products in a largely autonomous way.

- improved data handling for mobile and web clients by providing a faster, safer and more robust way to fetch data using GraphQL
- planned and played integral role in the development of bigger parts fo the GraphQL service like file uploads, caching and logged-out support

- increased availability, resilience and performance of the GraphQL service through systematic measurement, profiling, monitoring and implementation of the required changes
- built fast, secure, resilient and reliable HTTP level service to service communication
- created and carried out workshops to train engineers in GraphQL and Scala
- Provided architectural guidance and support for product teams to learn how to leverage GraphQL the best for their domains

leveraged knowledge

Scala, Ruby, GraphQL, Distributed Systems, RESTful APIs, AMQP, MySQL, HTTP, Network, Concurrency

XING Messenger End-to-End Encryption (2016 - 2017)

- planned, designed and documented the integration of a Double-Ratchet Protocol for the XING messenger together with external crypto experts
- designed and developed the backend integration to bring End-To-End Encryption to the XING Messenger
- coordinated work of mobile engineers, backend engineers and external experts to bring the required encryption knowledge into the team and enable the delivery of End-To-End Encryption

leveraged knowledge

Ruby, AMQP, Cryptography, MySQL, Network protocols

XING Messenger (2015 - 2016)

- introduced highly available, resilient and performant real-time update channel for the XING messenger
- designed and implemented new RESTful APIs to enable new features on the XING messenger
- developed load testing component to verify and measure the real time update channel of the XING messenger and conducted performance / load testing
- improved the quality of the code base by driving and supporting a software design shift that provided a better basis for the development of features

leveraged knowledge

Ruby, Ruby on Rails, Elixir, Phoenix AMQP, Cryptography, MySQL and network programming

Senior Software Developer OMCnet Internet Service GmbH 2007 - Nov 2015

- introduced more reliable and capable version of E-Mail policy service to enforce policies on the MTA
- automated operations workflows and developed solutions to manage a fleet of dedicated and shared servers
- designed, planned, set up and operated high-available solutions for storage and web services
- developed web based management interfaces for the dedicated and shared hosting environment
- introduced continuous integration pipeline to speed the delivery features for the internal products
- designed, setup and implement configuration as code with puppet

leveraged knowledge

Ruby, C/C++, Perl, Scheme, PostgresQL, MySQL, network protocols, operations

Software Developer

Claxx.net

2005 - 2007

- built a fully automated layout engine to generate parts of a magazine with sport-statistical data, which eliminated the need for a lengthy manual layout process
- developed web based Interface for external customers to leverage in-house sports data
- automate workflows in the production of a sports magazine

leveraged knowledge

Ruby, PHP, C/C++, Scheme, MSSQL, SXML, Quark

EDUCATION

Fernuniversität Hagen

Computer Science

2003 - 2006

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

- programming language theory
- callisthenics
- music / guitar